<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-olympics</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/item/sn97065832/1896-12-04/ed-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>It is interesting to ask oneself what
are likely to be the results of the
Olympic games of 1896, as regards both
Greece and the rest of the world. In
the case of Greece the games will be
found to have had a double effect, one
athletic, the other political. It is a
well-known fact that the Greeks had
lost completely, during their centuries
of oppression, the taste for physical
sports. There were good walkers
among the mountaineers, and good
swimmers in the scattered villages
along the coast. It was a matter of
pride with the young palikar to wrestle
and to dance well, but that was be
cause bravery and a gallant bearing
were admired by those about him.
Greek dances are far from athletic, and
the wrestling matches of peasants have
none of the characteristics of true
sports. The men of the towns had
come to know no diversion beyond
reading the newspapers and violently
discussing politics about the tables of
the cafes.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/item/sn83045462/1952-07-19/ed-1/</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>The Pres
ident of the Republic of Finland,
before 70,000 rain-soaked spec
tators, today opened the 15th
Olympic Games, the biggest in
history and the first to be attend
ed by Soviet Russia.
President Juho K. Paasikivi
and two Olympic officials wore
formal clothes, the only ones to
hold to custom on this solemn,
but sodden occasion.
As the band played the presi
dential salute the trio walked
down the line of the International
Olympic Committee, shaking
hands in the downpour.
Only about half of the Olympic
officials even bothered to wear
raincoats. The Finnish Olympic
Committee stuck to its gray suits.
Despite the rain, which started
about an hour before the games
opened, the Btands were practi
cally full. Only one side of the
modernistic stadium is covered.
Olympic Slogans Flashed.
After greeting the Olympic of
ficials, Paasikivi took his seat in
the President’s box.
The parade of the 5,870 athletes
from 69 nations taking part in
the games followed the alphabeti
cal order in Finnish, except that
Greece, as always, came first.
Finland came last as the home
team.
This brought the Netherlands
Antilles next after Greece, fol
lowed by Argentina. Russia,
which is Neuvostoliito in Finnish,
was midway in the parade.
400 Americans Parade.
The United States—Yhdysvallat
—was at the very end, just ahead
of Finland.
One of the biggest roars of ap
proval came from the 70,000 when
the United States team, 400 strong,
entered the arena. Norman C.
Armitage, a veteran New York
fencer, carried the Stars and
Stripes.
Just behind him, leading the
American delegation, was Avery
Brundage, head of the American
team and the newly elected presi
dent of the International Olympic
Committee..</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-sinking-maine</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85066387/1898-04-26/ed-1/?sp=1&q=SPAIN+War+war+Spain+WAR&st=image&r=-0.729,-0.092,2.458,1.216,0</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text>I recommend to your especial .-mention the note directed to the United States
Minister ;it Madrid by the Spanish Minister for Foreign Affairs on the .21st in
st&nt, whereby the foregoing notification was conveyed. It will be perceived
that toe Bpanish Government, having cognizance of the joint resolution of the
Congress of the United Estates, and In view of things which the President is
thereby required and authorised to do, responds by treating the demands of
this Government as measures of hostility, following with that instant and com
plete severance of relations by its action which, by usage of nations, accom
panies an existent state of war between sovereign powers.
The position of Spain being thus made known, and the demands of the
United States being denied, with a complete rupture In the intercourse with
Spnln. I have been constrained in the exercise of the power and authority con
ferred upon me by the joint resolution aforesaid to proclaim, under date of
April 22. IS9S. a blockade of certain ports of the north coast of Cuba, lying be
tween Cardenas and Bahia Honda, and of the port of Clenfuegos on the south
coast of Cuba; and further, in exercise of my constitutional powers, and using
the. authority conferred upon me by the act of Congress approved April 22,
1898, to Issue my proclamation dated April 23, IS9B, calling for volunteers in
order to carry into effect the said resolution of April 20, 1898. Copies of these
proclamations are hereunto appended.
In view of the measures so taken, and with a view to the adoption ,of
sucfa other measures as may be necessary to enable me to carry out the ex
pressed will of the Congress of the United States in the premises, I now recom
mend to your honorable body the adoption of a joint resolution declaring that
a Htate of war exists between the United States of America and the Kingdom
of Spain and I urge speedy action thereon to the end that the definition of
the international status of the United States as a belligerent power may be
made known, and the assertion of all its rights and the maintenance of all ita
duties in the conduct of a public war may be assured.
WILLIAM McKINLEY.
Executive Mansion, Washington, April 25, ISOB.
sixty seconds later The Call bulletin
service had flashed the news to San
Francisco that the resolutions had
been signed by the Chief Executive.
Now that all technicalities under
the strictest construction of interna-
The San Francisco Call
tional law have been complied with
and it has been advertised to the
world that we are at war with Spain,
the Navy Department is anxious to
give the order that will mean the
Continued on Second Page.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://www.loc.gov/resource/sn85054468/1898-04-19/ed-1/?sp=1&q=ACTIOS+maine+war</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text>Despite the fact that the center of in
terest clearly was in the other end of the
Capitol, when the Senate was called to
order at noon yesterday there were not
many vacant seats In the galleries.
Ladies predominated, as was the case
during the series of warm war debates of
last week, and they seemed to take great
interest in the routine proceedings and In
the presentation of minor bills which
marked the opening hours of the session,
they evidently having in mind the fact
that many of the men who yesterday were
speaking calmly of comparatively small
fry matters were the ones who, but a
few hours since, had thundered forth
their defiance to another nation and de
clared for war.
While to the casual observer the Senate
preserved its customary august mien, to
the experienced eye it was evident that
there was an undercurrent of anxiety as
to the action of the lower House on the
war and recognition resolutions of Sat
urday. There were several conferences
between the leaders on the two sides in
the Senate, both In the cloak-room and in
the chamber.
Mr. Rawlins of Utah arose to address
the Senate at 12:50 upon the distinctive
right of the President to recognize the
national Independence of Cuba. "It has
been contended," he said, "that the
power to recognize the international In
dependence of Cuba rests with the Pres
iJent. That power ought not to be exer
cised. I desire to discuss the question on
the provisions of the Constitution. The
power to recognize national independence
.s not conferred, in express terms, on the
President or any department of the Gov
ernment. Heretofore it has existed as an
incidental authorization." He then cited
numerous decisions by the United States
Supreme Court bearing upon the question
and upon which he made no comment.
ot an Ka-ocutiie Function.
Mr. Rawlings held that the recognition
of national independence by the President
would be subject to review by the Senate.
The right has been but incidental to his
power to receive foreign ambassadors,
which right Is not conferred upon him,
by the way, in any part of the Constitu
tion. Mr. Rawlins declared that the
pow er to declare war is vested exclusively
in the Congress and that the President
Las no right to receive any foreign repre
c r.taflves until a declaration of -war shall
hi.c been made A declaration of war
t: a. y destroys all existing treaties be
tween the countries at war, and It alto
breaks off diplomatic relations.
If the President should recognize na
tional independence, the Congress dis
tantly has the right to wipe out all ihe
trea es or other recognition which may
1-j.ve neon maue. tJongre&s also may
snatch away from the Executive the right
10 rcceic foreign ambassadors, he de
clared. W hik Mr. Rawlins was speaking Gen.
Grrsror came over from the Hous-e
r.d went directly to Mr. Hanna's seat.
H talked with the Senator from Ohio for
several moments and then repaired to the
lower chamber.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-wwi-christmas-truce</id>
    <results>
      <result>
	<id>/https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn94050892/1914-12-25/ed-1/seq-4/#words=Christmas+days+truce</id>
	<rel>1</rel>
	<text>A CHRISTMAS TRUCE.'
Armies have always seemed to ha a pre
diction. for righting great battles on Sunday
Even Christmas day has not been held sacred as
a day of peace. It would be a logical climax .of
the present conflict of Christendom if the ap
proaching Christmas should mark an orgy of
slaughter. f ,
Pope Benedict has taken the initiative in a
step aiming at the prevention of a tragedy so
checking to the moral sense of humanity. He
has suggested that the belligerents agree to ' a
truce during the Christmas holidays. Germany
is reported to favor the proposal, on condition
that her enen.ies consent to t. ' '
. The efforts . of the Vatican are . seconded "at
Washington in a joint congressional resolution
requesting the warring nations to declare a
Christmas truce of twenty days. It is not likely
that the powers will agree to stop fighting -for
so long as that; but any cessation of hostilities
at all would be a grateful relief to the world as
well as fo the lighters. It would also tend,' in
the language of the Ketiyon resolution, to
"stimulate reOection upon the part of the-belli
gerent nations as to the meaning and , spirit of
the Christmas time, to the end that there may
come again 'on earth peace, good will toward
men. " Even Turkey and Japan, to whom the
Christmas traditions means " nothing, might
derive benefit from such a course.</text>
      </result>
      <result>
	<id>/https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84022835/1914-12-31/ed-1/seq-6/#words=Christmas+Truce</id>
	<rel>0</rel>
	<text>No Christmas Truce.
iLondon. Instead of tho Christmas
truce which Popo Benedict endeavored
to arrange. Christmas found the armies
of tho belligerent powers engaged In
llorco battles on both tho eastern and
western fronts. In tho west tho allies'
hammer is tapping at tho German en
trenchments, trying to And a weak
point, whllo In the east tho Russians,
who have been driven back from tho
Austrian and German frontiers, seem
ingly have been brought to bay bo
hind rivers which offer them natural
lines of defonso, and turning hnvo
counter-attacked the GermanRusslan
forces.</text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
